<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://aaronwatts.dev/tech/feed.xml" rel="self" type="applications/rss+xml" />
    <title>AaronWattsDev Latest</title>
    <link>https://aaronwatts.dev/tech</link>
    <description>The most recent content on AaronWattsDev</description>
    <category>Technology</category>
    <item>
      <title>Kobo - E-Reader</title>
      <link>https://aaronwatts.dev/tech/kobo-ereader</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>Kobo e-reader's won't do too much more than an Amazon Kindle, unless you are outside of the US. Kobo do just enough differently that I'd consider them to be thoughtful technology.</description>
      <guid>https://aaronwatts.dev/tech/kobo-ereader</guid>
      <content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Kobo - E-Reader&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;time datetime="2025-05-23"&gt;23&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; May, 2025&lt;/time&gt;&lt;img alt="It looks like the developer forgot to include alt text" src="https://aaronwatts.dev/images/tech/kobo-ereader.jpg"/&gt;&lt;p id="intro"&gt; Kobo e-reader's won't do too much more than an Amazon Kindle, unless you are outside of the US. Kobo do just enough differently that I'd consider them to be thoughtful technology. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; I can resist a trend, and tend not to jump onto very many things early. Amazon was one of those things. One of my first experiences with Amazon, that I still encounter today, is older relatives asking how to cancel a subscription that they didn't know they had. This happens a lot, it's like Amazon design their interfaces to intentionally trick people who are not tech literate into accidentally subscribing to additional services. And Kindle may be the biggest offender in that respect. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; My mum is one such tech illiterate person, and the problem had become common enough to put her off trying to use her Kindle. E-readers tend to be pretty locked down in terms of software, so unless you are able to make modifications or track down an obscure model that is probably not suitable for tech noobs, then you're kind of stuck with what you get out of the box. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; While looking for a different device for my mum, I found out about &lt;a href="https://www.overdrive.com/apps/libby" target="_blank"&gt;Libby and Overdrive&lt;/a&gt;, an e-book library system. I thought this was amazing, and wondered why it wasn't included as standard in Kindle's. I later found out that it is in fact included in Kindles, but not outside of the United States. However, I soon discovered that the &lt;a href="https://www.kobo.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt; e-readers do include Overdrive, even here in the UK. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Overdrive requires a library card for your local library, and despite being digital, there are only so many copies of a e-book that can be &lt;em&gt;"borrowed"&lt;/em&gt;, so it can be a bit of a wait for more popular titles, if they are even available at all. My mum is an keen and unfussy reader, so despite the limitations, this is a perfect system for her. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; After setting up a Kobo for my mum, I was pleased with what I was seeing, and &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; made the transition from paper to electronic books myself, although I keep mine offline and manage my own library using the &lt;a href="https://calibre-ebook.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Calibre&lt;/a&gt; e-book management software. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded>
      <enclosure url="https://aaronwatts.dev/images/tech/kobo-ereader.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg" />
      <media:thumbnail url="https://aaronwatts.dev/images/tech/kobo-ereader.jpg" width="1920" height="1080" />
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://aaronwatts.dev/images/tech/kobo-ereader.jpg" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fairphone - Smartphone</title>
      <link>https://aaronwatts.dev/tech/fairphone</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>Fairphone, based in Netherlands, brings something back to smartphones that most people don't even realise is missing. Their approach aims to promote user ownership of a device, and longevity.</description>
      <guid>https://aaronwatts.dev/tech/fairphone</guid>
      <content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Fairphone - Smartphone&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;time datetime="2025-05-07"&gt;7&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; May, 2025&lt;/time&gt;&lt;img alt="An exploded view of the replacable modilar components that mke up the fairphone 4" src="https://aaronwatts.dev/images/tech/fairphone.jpg"/&gt;&lt;p id="intro"&gt; Fairphone, based in Netherlands, brings something back to smartphones that most people don't even realise is missing. Their approach aims to promote user ownership of a device, and longevity. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; While they may not necessarily be hitting their mark in terms of longevity &lt;em&gt;just yet&lt;/em&gt; (the Fairphone 4 won't really have had a much longer lifespan than most other Android devices when it reaches the current proposed EOL), &lt;a href="https://www.fairphone.com/en" target="_blank"&gt;Fairphone&lt;/a&gt; are certainly achieving their goals with regard to user ownership. They issue instructions on how to unlock the bootloader on their phones, and they have made it incredibly easy to self repair with their modular design. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; My biggest gripe about smartphones, is that it costs a fortune to fix if you break it. I don't like contracts, I try to steer clear of the subscription society that has become ubiquitous nowadays, so phone repair can get a little pricey. After breaking the screen on my Samsung a second time, I realised I was beginning to get close to the price for an entirely new handset if I took it in to get it fixed again. So I didn't. I got a Fairphone 4, which has a modular design, which means I could repair a screen at home for only £70. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Device/Fairphone_4" target="_blank"&gt;Ifixit&lt;/a&gt; have given the Fairphone 4 a repairability score of 10/10. Fairphone are still selling replacement parts for the Fairphone 3 and even 2 in their parts store. Hopefully, with a little more experience they can get the shelf life of their handsets to where they want them to be. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded>
      <enclosure url="https://aaronwatts.dev/images/tech/fairphone.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg" />
      <media:thumbnail url="https://aaronwatts.dev/images/tech/fairphone.jpg" width="1920" height="1080" />
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://aaronwatts.dev/images/tech/fairphone.jpg" />
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>